Guide to the Music Department Records: Series 3, Concert Programs, 1863-[ongoing]
Music Department Records: Series 3, Concert Programs, 1863-[ongoing]
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Music Dept.
1000-182
3.5
7
The music program at Wesleyan University dates back to the early days of the institution, when informal singing groups performed for special occasions. As the program expanded and became more formalized, courses were offered, and in 1929 the Music Department was established. Performance groups came to include the Glee Club, the Chapel Choir, the Choral Society, the Jibers, the Cardinals, the Wesleyan Band, and a number of instrumental ensembles. During the 1950s, associate professor David McAllester introduced world music courses into the curriculum, and in 1966 the department established a doctoral program in ethnomusicology. Visiting artists from various regions around the world, including Africa, India, Indonesia, Japan, and Korea, have performed at the university.
Series 3, Concert Programs, contains programs for musical performances held at Wesleyan University. Performers include Wesleyan and non-Wesleyan musicians. A small group of organ concerts is listed first, followed by concerts of all types in chronological order. This collection is incomplete. For the guide to the complete Music Department Records, please see http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/mu1000-182.html
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Concert programs given by the Music Department and collected from other sources by the University Archives. Programs will be periodically added as received by the Archives.
Historical Note
Music has been part of the Wesleyan University experience since the early days of the institution. Known as a "singing college," Wesleyan inherited a tradition of music from the hymnody of its Methodist roots (see David B. Potts's Wesleyan University, 1831-1910: Collegiate Enterprise in New England). The first music performances at the university were organized by volunteers and sponsored by groups such as the Middlesex Musical Association. Beginning in the 1840s, glee clubs were created for special occasions, and in 1862 Wesleyan singers had their first public tour. In 1882 the university hired a professional musician as glee club coach, and the group gave standing-room-only public appearances, including an 1888 concert at the Metropolitan Opera House in New York City. From the 1880s on, undergraduate students as well as alumni composed songs; these were collected in the Wesleyan Song Book, first published in 1901. Weekly sings took place on the chapel steps beginning in about 1901, and in about 1913 the university began offering a small stipend to students who participated in the chapel choir.
During the 1920s, the music program at Wesleyan became more formalized. In 1921, the Music and Dramatics Board was created to supervise musical and dramatic organizations and arrange concerts and trips. The university also offered its first course work in music. In the academic year 1925/26, Hugh L. Smith (class of 1915), an assistant professor in the Department of Romance Languages, offered a course on the history and appreciation of music. In 1928/29, courses in dramatic music and harmony were added. Then, in 1929, alumnus John Spencer Camp (class of 1878) donated a large sum to set up a chair of music at the university. Joseph Stephen Daltry was appointed to the newly endowed chair, and the Music Department was established.
The music program at Wesleyan continued to expand over the years. By the late 1940s, two professors--Joseph Daltry and George McManus--were offering about ten courses a year. In 1949, Richard Winslow (class of 1940) joined the staff. By the mid-1950s, singers performed not only with the Chapel Choir and Glee Club but also with the Choral Society, a male quartet called the Jibers, and a group of eight or nine called the Cardinals. The Wesleyan Band performed at football games and various campus affairs, and a woodwind and brass ensemble played several recitals a year. The Music Department, at that time housed in Judd Hall, had several sound-proof studios and an extensive collection of phonograph records. By the late 1960s, musical opportunities at the university included private lessons; the Wesleyan University concert series; the college orchestra, a "town-gown" organization; the Wesleyan String Quartet; and the Collegium Musicum, which performed medieval and Renaissance music.
A significant development in the music program that occurred around the middle of the twentieth century was the introduction of the study of music "as a universal phenomenon beyond the confines of Western European tradition" (Wesleyan University Bulletin, 1956/57). In 1956/57, associate professor David McAllester, an anthropologist whose specialty was the culture and music of the Navajo, first offered Music 31, Ethnic and Folk Music, in addition to the anthropology courses he taught in the Department of Psychology. In 1961, McAllester teamed up with Robert E. Brown, a specialist in the music of India, to teach classes in the university's new World Music Program. McAllester and Richard Winslow proposed an advanced program of study, and in 1966 the department began offering a doctorate in ethnomusicology in addition to undergraduate and master's degrees. By the 1970s, courses taught by resident and visiting members of the department's faculty covered Western classical, Afro-American, South Indian, North Indian, and Japanese music; the 1970/71 catalog listed some thirty-two courses and seminars in non-Western music. Study groups were organized focusing on the music of South India, Japan, Persia, Korea, and the Javanese gamelan.
In 1973, Wesleyan opened its Center for the Arts, a complex of eleven buildings housing undergraduate programs in art and art history, dance, theater, and music, as well as the graduate program in ethnomusicology. The Center comprises classrooms, galleries, and studios, and its music facilities include a recording studio, a computer and experimental music studio, Crowell Concert Hall, and World Music Hall.
The Music Department currently provides course work and performing opportunities in music from around the world. More than sixty courses are offered. A number of activities--including a variety of chamber ensembles and ensembles in Asian, African, American, and European traditions--are available to students. Music facilities include a collection of instruments from many different cultures; a music-instrument manufacturing workshop; a scores and recordings collection; and a world music archives. An ongoing departmental colloquium presents lectures on issues in the world of music by students, faculty, and outside speakers. In addition, the department sponsors events such as concerts by world-renowned jazz artists, the Wesleyan World Percussion Festival (2000), New England Gamelan Weekend (2002), the Celtic Routes Festival (2003), and the annual Navaratri Festival.
Collection Overview
Series 3, Concert Programs, contains programs for musical performances held at Wesleyan University. Performers include Wesleyan and non-Wesleyan musicians. A small group of organ concerts is listed first, followed by concerts of all types in chronological order. This collection is incomplete.
For the guide to the complete Music Department Records, please see http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/mu1000-182.html
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Music Dept.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Songs and music.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Concerts--Connecticut--Middletown.; Programs (documents)
Related Material
Some concerts may have recordings available in Scores & Recordings; check the Wesleyan catalog for availability. Some concert posters may be available in Special Collections & Archives.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 3. Concert Programs, 1878-[ongoing]
  7 boxes (3.5 linear feet)
  - Organ Concerts
    - February 12th, 1886: Wesleyan University Octette, performed by Warbler, F.R. Bouton, Pianist, W.F. Dales, Manager, C.D. Burdick (Box 1)
    - May 30th, 1898: Organ Recital, performed by Mr. C.R. Smith; Mr. Frederick Vinal, of Hartford-Tenor (Box 1)
    - June 6th, 1898: Organ Recital, performed by Mr. C.R. Smith; Miss Ada Austin, Soprano; Mr. Frederick Vinal, tenor; Miss Emma Buch, Alto; Mr. W. B. Davis, Bass (Box 1)
    - March 8th, 1899: Organ Recital, performed by Mr. Clarence Robertson Smith Assisted by Mr. Ion A. Jackson (Box 1)
    - March 20th, 1899: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mr. Clarence Robertson Smith Assisted by Miss Helene R. Rass (Box 1)
    - April 11th, 1899: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mr. Clarence Robertson Smith Assisted by Miss Ada M. Austin (Box 1)
    - October 17th, 1899: Concert (2 copies), performed by Dr. Minor C. Baldwin of Chickering Hall, New York City (Box 1)
    - October 17th, 1899: Memorial Chapel Orgain Recital (2 copies), performed by Dr. Minor C. Baldwin of Chickering Hall, New York City Assisted by Miss Evelyn Maud Webster (Box 1)
    - January 30th, 1900: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mr. Clarence Robertson Smith, Assisted by Mr. Thomas H. Montgomery (Box 1)
    - March 27th, 1900: Organ Recital, performed by Mr. Clarence Robertson Smith, Assisted by Mr. Alfred Barrington (Box 1)
    - May 8th, 1902: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mr. Arthur C. Lunn, Assisted by Mr. H. H. Smith and University Quartette (Box 1)
    - October 1st, 1916: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Dr. Minor C. Baldwin (Box 1)
    - October 23rd, 1916: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by John Spencer Camp (Box 1)
    - November 21st, 1916: Organ Recital in Memorial Chapel (2 copies), performed by Joseph Clair Beebe (Box 1)
    - February 23rd, 1917: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Professor Karl Pomeroy Harrington (Box 1)
    - January 13th, 1918: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Latham True, Mus. D. (Box 1)
    - February 22nd, 1918: Organ Recital, performed by Professor Karl Pomeroy Harrington (Box 1)
    - Fecruary 7th, 1999: Four Joint Recitals (2 copies), performed by Binney Gunnison, Edward Austin Warren, JR (Box 1)
    - February 20th, 1920: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Professor Karl Pomeroy Harrington (Box 1)
    - April 2nd and 3rd, 1920: The Classical Association of New England Fifteenth Annual Meeting, performed by Mr. J. Clair Beebe, Wesleyan '07 (Box 1)
    - June 2nd, 1922: Fine Arts Club: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by T. Tertius Noble, M.A., F.R.C.O (Box 1)
    - October 30th, 1922: In Recital (2 copies), performed by Warren D. Allen (Box 1)
    - April 29th, 1926: Organ Recital, performed by Chandler Goldthwaite (Box 1)
    - October 15th, 1926: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mr. Chandler Goldthwaite (Box 1)
    - January 9th, 1927: Vesper Music (2 copies), performed by Mr. H. Frank Bozyan (Box 1)
    - November 8th, 1927: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mr. Chandler Goldthwaite (Box 1)
    - February 19th, 1928: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Harry Benjamin Jepson (Box 1)
    - March 18th, 1928: Organ Recital, performed by Hugh Llewellyn Smith (Box 1)
    - October 15th, 1929: Organ Recital, performed by Chandler Goldthwaite (Box 1)
    - March 2nd, 1930: Organ Recital, performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - March 30th, 1930: Joint Recital (2 copies), performed by Thomas W. Bussom, Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - January 18th, 1931: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - February 15th,1931: Joint Recital (2 copies), performed by Thomas W. Bussom, Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - March 8th, 1931: Organ Recital, performed by Arthur Jennings (Box 1)
    - May 13th, 1931: Organ Recital, performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - October 11th, 1931: Organ Recital, performed by Arthur B. Jennings, JR.,'10 (Box 1)
    - December 6th, 1931: Recital, performed by Chorp McClusky, pianist; Joseph S. Daltry, organist (Box 1)
    - March 6th, 1932: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by E. Harold Geer (Box 1)
    - November 13th, 1932: Joint Recital, Piano-Organ, performed by Richard Malaby, Pianist; Joseph Daltry, Organist (Box 1)
    - April 19th, 1933: Organ Recital, performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - November 26th, 1933: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - January 21st, 1934: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - November 4th, 1934: Organ Recital, performed by Myron D. Casner (Box 1)
    - November 13th, 1935: Recital, performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - March 18th, 1936: Organ Recital, performed by John B. Carroll (Box 1)
    - March 14th, 1937: Program of Music for Two Piano and Organ, performed by Joseph S. Daltry, Charles R. Nichols, John B. Carroll (Box 1)
    - October 13th, 1937: Organ Recital, performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - Fridays March and April 1938: Historical Organ Recitals (2 copies), performed by Charles R. Nichols and assisting soloists (Box 1)
    - Fridays March and April 1938: Musical Programs (2 copies), performed by Charles R. Nichols (Box 1)
    - May 22nd, 1938: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Harold E. Darke (Box 1)
    - June 17th,1938: Works by American College Professors, performed by Charles R. Nichols (Box 1)
    - April 15th, 1942: Organ Recital of the Works of J.S. Bach, performed by Joseph S. Daltry (Box 1)
    - May 23rd, 1944: Organ Recital, performed by Helen Hewitt (Box 1)
    - January 29th, 1946: Vesper Organ Recital, performed by Edward H. Hastings (Box 1)
    - April 2nd, 1946: Vesper Organ Recital, performed by Edward H. Hastings (Box 1)
    - October 4th, 1963: Music of Johann Sebastian Bach, performed by E. Power Biggs, organist (Box 1)
    - November 18th, 1964: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Mary Frances Ross (Box 1)
    - January 17th, 1965: Program (2 copies), performed by Philip A. Prince (Box 1)
    - February 7th, 1965: Music at the Honors College (2 copies), performed by John Fenstermaker, '64, organist (Box 1)
    - February 28th, 1965: Program J.S. Bach (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - March 21st, 1965: Program (2 copies), performed by H. Frank Bozyan (Box 1)
    - April 7th, 1965: (2 copies), performed by Piet Kee, organist (Box 1)
    - November 18th, 1965: (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - December 1st, 1965: (2 copies), performed by Philip A. Prince (Box 1)
    - January 16th, 1966: Music at the Honors College (2 copies), performed by John Fenstermaker, organist (Box 1)
    - February 2nd, 1966: Program (2 copies), performed by B. Lynn Herbert (Box 1)
    - May 18th, 1966: Organ Recital (2 copies), performed by Myrtle Regier (Box 1)
    - October 24th, 1966: Program, performed by Linda Jane Clark (Box 1)
    - November 9th, 1966: Program (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - February 6th, 1967: Program (2 copies), performed by Robert Gronquist, organist (Box 1)
    - March 5th, 1967: Music at the Honors College (2 copies), performed by John Fenstermaker, '64, organist (Box 1)
    - April 23rd, 1967: Program (2 copies), performed by Philip Prince (Box 1)
    - October 30th, 1967: Program (2 copies), performed by Linda Jane Clark, organist (Box 1)
    - November 27th, 1967: Program (2 copies), performed by Philip Prince (Box 1)
    - January 14th, 1968: Program (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - April 28th, 1968: Program (2 copies), performed by George Blackburn (Box 1)
    - May 12th, 1968: Program (2 copies), performed by Allan Birney (Box 1)
    - November 4th, 1968: Program (2 copies), performed by Myrtle Regier (Box 1)
    - December 2nd, 1968: Program (2 copies), performed by Marion R. Anderson (Box 1)
    - April 17th, 1969: Program (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - May 8th, 1969: A Program of Organ Music by Johann Gottfried Walther (2 copies), performed by Philip Prince (Box 1)
    - October 26th, 1969: Program (2 copies), performed by George Butler (Box 1)
    - November 19th, 1969: Program (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - February 15th, 1970: Music at the Honors College (2 copies), performed by John Fenstermaker (Box 1)
    - April 13th, 1970: A Program of Organ Music (2 copies), performed by Philip Prince (Box 1)
    - September 21st, 1970: Program (2 copies), performed by William Osborne (Box 1)
    - November 6th, 1970: Program (2 copies), performed by Roger Evans (Box 1)
    - April 21st, 1971: Program (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - May 13th, 1971: Program (2 copies), performed by Philip Prince (Box 1)
    - October 25th, 1971: Program (2 copies), performed by Linda Clark (Box 1)
    - January 24th, 1972: Program (2 copies), performed by David Johnson (Box 1)
    - February 20th, 1972: Program (2 copies), performed by Michael Hunter (Box 1)
    - February 20th,1972: Program (2 Copies) diferent format from above, performed by Michael Hunter (Box 1)
    - February 28th, 1972: Program (2 copies), performed by Kurt Lueders (Box 1)
    - April 19th, 1972: A Musical Trip Around Europe (2 copies), performed by Charles Krigbaum (Box 1)
    - May 10th, 1972: A Program of Organ Music by Deitrich Buxtehude (2 copies), performed by Philip Prince (Box 1)
  - General Concerts
    - July 15, (1863?): Grand Concert!, performed by Dodworth's Band (Box 1)
    - March 8, 1864: Concert of Gilmore's Band, performed by Gilmore's Band (Box 1)
    - November 21, 1864: Grand Concert!, performed by Hall's Band (Box 1)
    - July 19, (1865?): Commencement Concert, performed by Germania Band (Box 1)
    - October 25, 1867: Grand Concert, performed by Diamond Octette (Box 1)
    - 1868?: Commencement Concert, performed by Grafulla's 7th Regiment Band (Box 1)
    - 1869?: Commencement Concert, performed by Gilmore's Band (Box 1)
    - 1870?: Commencement Concert, performed by Quintette Club (Box 1)
    - February 24, 1874: An Evening With Barnabee, performed by W.U. Boat Club Course (Box 1)
    - May 25, 1874: Musical Soiree, performed by Students and the Orpheus Amateur Orchestra (Box 1)
    - April 29, 1875: Benefit Concert, performed by Boat Club (Box 1)
    - June 21, 1876: Benefit Concert, performed by None listed (Box 1)
    - May 10, 1878: Benefit Concert, performed by Addie Haight, Mrs. Post, Mrs. E.A. Parsons, Mr. Andrus, Fred Guilford, Mr. E.A. Parsons, Wesleyan Quartette, W.W. Pearne, Fred Ingraham (Box 1)
    - June 26, 1878: Grand Commencement Concert, performed by American Band of Providence (Box 1)
    - December 9, 1879: Concerte, performed by "All ye Men and Women Singers" (Box 1)
    - March 26, 1882: Service of Song, performed by Choir and student speakers (Box 1)
    - June 30, 1885: Class Day Concert, performed by Listemann Concert Company, Temple Quartet, Maud Morgan, E.M. Heindl, E.F. Webber (Box 1)
    - June 19, 1887: Service of Song, performed by Choir and student speakers (Box 1)
    - June 22, 1891: Concert, performed by Severn's Orchestra (Box 1)
    - November 20, 1920: Concert and Dance, performed by Wesleyan University clubs (Box 1)
    - February 15, 1904: The Kneisel Quartet, performed by Franz Kneisel, J. Theodorowicz, Louis Svecenski, Alwin Schroeder (Box 1)
    - June 27, 1905: Musicale, performed by Brothers of Psi Upsilon (Box 1)
    - June 20, 1908: The Girl and the Graduate, performed by Wesleyan Musical Association (Box 1)
    - May 19, 1909: Musicale, performed by Assorted clubs (Box 1)
    - April 11, 1918: Musicale, performed by Center Church Quartette (Box 1)
    - June 4, 1921: Fine Arts Club Musicale, performed by Miss Dacier, Miss Hull, Mr. Multer, Mrs. Farley, Heidel, Wilkinson, James, Messrs. Malsley, Knowles and Strickland (Box 1)
    - December 16, 1922: Nina Morgana, Soprano, performed by Nina Morgana. Accompanied on piano by Kathryn Kerin (Box 1)
    - January 23, 1923: Three Centuries of Songs by English Composers, performed by Francis Rogers (Box 1)
    - December 9, 1924: Rachmaninoff, performed by C.J. Foley (Box 1)
    - February 17, 1925: Suzanne Keener, Soprano, performed by Suzanne Keener (Box 1)
    - April 29, 1925: Boston Symphony Orchestral Group, performed by Boston Symphony Orchestral Group (Box 1)
    - November 20, 1925: Costume Song Recital, performed by Vandalia H. Burgy, Mrs. Charles A. Saxton (Box 1)
    - November 30, 1925: Mischa Elman, Celebrated Violinist, performed by Mischa Elman (Box 1)
    - January 14, 1926: Ethyl Hayden, Soprano. Howard Goding. Pianist, performed by Ethyl Hayden, Howard Goding (Box 1)
    - February 11, 1926: The London String Quartet, performed by James Levey, Thomas W. Petre, H. Waldo Warner, C. Warwick-Evans (Box 1)
    - April 8, 1926: The Brahms Quartet, performed by Gladys Halstead, Zilla Wilson, Nancy Hitch, Elinor Markey (Box 1)
    - May 24, 1926: Four-hand Recital, performed by Mr. and Mrs. Hugh L. Smith (Box 1)
    - January 13, 1927: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by George Barrere, Michael de Stefano, Alberico Guidi, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - February 13, 1927: Vesper Music, performed by Bruce Simonds (Box 1)
    - March 10, 1927: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by Bernard Ocko, Louis Kaufman, Marie Roemaet Rosanoff, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - March 31, 1927: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by Mina Hager, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - April 28, 1927: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by Gilbert Ross, Isadore Berv, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - May 26, 1927: No title, performed by Dorothy Hull, Alice Sitterly, Frances Warner, Banoroft Sitterly (Box 1)
    - Spring 1927 (no date on program): Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - December 29, 1927: Concert, performed by The Combined Musical Clubs of Wesleyan University (Box 1)
    - No date.: Barnabee Concert, performed by Mr. Barnabee (Box 1)
    - February 16, 1930: Harp Recital, performed by Mildred Dilling (Box 1)
    - February 23, 1930: Piano Recital, performed by Bruce Simonds (Box 1)
    - March 16, 1930: Violin Recital, performed by Hugo Kortschak (Box 1)
    - March 21, 1930: Song Recital, performed by Earle Spicer (Box 1)
    - November 23, 1930: Harp Recital, performed by Mildred Dilling (Box 1)
    - January 11, 1931: No title, performed by The Barbizon String Quartet, John Erskine (Box 1)
    - January 25, 1931: Piano Recital, performed by Bruce Simonds (Box 1)
    - February 22, 1931: Piano Recital, performed by Gottfried Galston (Box 1)
    - March 15, 1931: Violin Recital, performed by Harold Berkley (Box 1)
    - April 12, 1931: No title, performed by Wesleyan Concert Choir, Faith Merriam, Thomas W. Bussom, Frank B. Stover (Box 1)
    - January 12, 1928: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by George Barrere, Michael de Stefano, Walter Edelstein, Mitja Stillman, Alberico Guidi, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - February 23, 1928: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - March 8, 1928: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by Gilbert Ross, Naoum Benditzky, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - March 22, 1928: Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by John Goss, Arthur Whiting (Box 1)
    - Spring 1928 (no date given in program): Expositions of Classical and Modern Chamber Music, performed by The New York String Quartet (Box 1)